I want you to look around the room for a minute
أُريد منكم أن تنظروا حول الغرفة لدقيقة
and try to find the most paranoid person here --
وتحاولوا إيجاد أكثر شخص مريض بجنون العظمة هنا--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then I want you to point at that person for me.
ومن ثمَّ أُريد منكم أن تُشيروا لي على هذا الشخص.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
OK, don't actually do it.
حسناً، لاتفعلوا هذا حقاً.
But, as an organizational psychologist,
ولكن كعالِم نفس تنظيمي،
I spend a lot of time in workplaces,
قضيت الكثير مِن الوقت في أماكن العمل،
and I find paranoia everywhere.
ووجدت جنون العظمة في كل مكان.
Paranoia is caused by people that I call "takers."
من قِبل ناس أُسميهم "الإستغلاليون".
Takers are self-serving in their interactions.
الإستغلاليون يخدمون مصالحهم الشخصية.
It's all about what can you do for me.
كل ما يهُم في الأمر هو ماتستطيع تقديمه لي.
The opposite is a giver.
العكس من هذا المُعطي.
It's somebody who approaches most interactions by asking,
هو الشخص الذي دائماً ما يسألك،
"What can I do for you?"
"ما الذي أستطيع القيام به لأجلك؟"
I wanted to give you a chance to think about your own style.
أُريد أن أعطيكم فرصة لتفكروا بأسلوبكم.
We all have moments of giving and taking.
الجميع لديه لحظات من الأخذ والعطاء.
Your style is how you treat most of the people most of the time,
وأسلوبك هو كيفية تعاملك مع أغلب الناس في أغلب الوقت،
your default.
هو شخصيتك الاعتيادية.
I have a short test you can take
لدي إختبار صغير لتفعلوه
to figure out if you're more of a giver or a taker,
وتكتشفوا إذا كنتم آخذين أو مِعطائين أكثر،
and you can take it right now.
بإمكانكم القيام به الآن.
[The Narcissist Test]
(إختبار النرجسية)
[Step 1: Take a moment to think about yourself.]
الخطوة 1،فكر في نفسك لبعض الوقت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
[Step 2: If you made it to Step 2, you are not a narcissist.]
الخطوة 2 ، إن إنتقلت إلى الخطوة الثانية إذاً لست نرجسي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is the only thing I will say today that has no data behind it,
هذا الشيء الوحيد الذي سأقوله بدون بيانات تدعمه،
but I am convinced the longer it takes for you to laugh at this cartoon,
ولكني مقتنع بأنه كلما أخذت وقتاً أكبر لتضحك علي الكرتون،
the more worried we should be that you're a taker.
كلما شعرنا بالقلق كونك شخص إستغلالي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Of course, not all takers are narcissists.
بالطبع ليس كل إستغلالي نرجسي.
Some are just givers who got burned one too many times.
البعض منهم كانوا معطائين و خُدِعوا أكثر مِن مرة .
Then there's another kind of taker that we won't be addressing today,
ومن ثم هناك نوع آخر من الإستغلاليين لن نُخاطبهم اليوم ،
and that's called a psychopath.
ويُدعون المرضى النفسيين
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I was curious, though, about how common these extremes are,
كنت فضولياً حول مدى إنتشار هذه الأفكار،
and so I surveyed over 30,000 people across industries
ولذلك أجريت استبيان على 30 ألف شخص
around the world's cultures.
مِن ثقافات مختلفة .
And I found that most people are right in the middle
وجدت بأن أغلب الناس في المنتصف
between giving and taking.
بين الأخذ والعطاء .
They choose this third style called "matching."
لقد إختاروا ما يُسمي بالتماثل .
If you're a matcher, you try to keep an even balance of give and take:
إن كنت توازن بين الأخذ والعطاء فانت شخص مُماثِل(يعامل بالمثل )
quid pro quo -- I'll do something for you if you do something for me.
مُقايضة - أفعل لك شئ في مقابل شئ تفعله لي-
And that seems like a safe way to live your life.
ويبدوا أن هذه طريقة ملائمة.
But is it the most effective and productive way to live your life?
ولكن هل هي الأكثر كفاءة وإنتاجية ؟
The answer to that question is a very definitive ...
الإجابة على هذا السؤال حاسمة ...
maybe.
ربما .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I studied dozens of organizations,
درست الكثير من المنظمات،
thousands of people.
ألآف الناس.
I had engineers measuring their productivity.
قمت بقياس إنتاجية المهندسين
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I looked at medical students' grades --
بحثت في درجات طلبة الطب ،
even salespeople's revenue.
حتي مندوبي المبيعات .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And, unexpectedly,
وعلي عكس المتوقَّع
the worst performers in each of these jobs were the givers.
الأقل أداء في هذه الوظائف كان المِعطاؤن.
The engineers who got the least work done
المهندسون الأقل إنجازاً لعملهم
were the ones who did more favors than they got back.
هم من يقوموا بخدمات أكثر مما يتلقون
They were so busy doing other people's jobs,
هم مشغولون بعمل وظائف الآخرين ،
they literally ran out of time and energy to get their own work completed.
فينفذ منهم الوقت والطاقة لإكمال عملهم الخاص.
In medical school, the lowest grades belong to the students
في كلية الطب ،الطلاب الأقل في الدرجات
who agree most strongly with statements like,
هم من يتفقون مع عِبارة،
"I love helping others,"
"أُحب مساعدة الآخرين "
which suggests the doctor you ought to trust
وهذه يوضح لنا الأطباء الممكن أن تثق بهم
is the one who came to med school with no desire to help anybody.
هم الذين يأتون لكلية الطب ولا يساعدون الآخرين .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And then in sales, too, the lowest revenue accrued
وفي المبيعات أيضاً، الأقل مبيعات
in the most generous salespeople.
هو المندوب الأكثر كرماً.
I actually reached out to one of those salespeople
تواصلت بالفعل مع أحد المندوبين
who had a very high giver score.
كثيري العطاء
And I asked him, "Why do you suck at your job --"
وسألته، "لماذا أنت سئ في وظيفتك --"
I didn't ask it that way, but --
لم اسأل بهذا الأسلوب طبعاً ، لكن
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"What's the cost of generosity in sales?"
"ما هي نتيجة الكرم في وظيفة كالمبيعات ؟"
And he said, "Well, I just care so deeply about my customers
وقال ،"حسناً ، أنا أهتم كثيراً بعملائي
that I would never sell them one of our crappy products."
لذا لن أبيع لهم أي مِن منتجاتنا السيئة."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So just out of curiosity,
من باب الفضول ،
how many of you self-identify more as givers than takers or matchers?
كم منكم يعتبر نفسه شخص مُعطي أكثر من كونه آخِذ؟
Raise your hands.
إرفعوا أيديكم .
OK, it would have been more before we talked about these data.
حسناً، كان العدد ليكون أكبر قبل عرض هذه البيانات.
But actually, it turns out there's a twist here,
وفي الحقيقة ،إتضح بأن هناك تغيير هنا ،
because givers are often sacrificing themselves,
لأن المِعطائين يضحون بأنفسهم ،
but they make their organizations better.
لكنهم يجعلوا منظماتهم أفضل
We have a huge body of evidence --
لدينا أدلة كثيرة--
many, many studies looking at the frequency of giving behavior
الكثير من الدراسات بحثت في سلوك العطاء
that exists in a team or an organization --
الموجودة في فريق أو منظمة--
and the more often people are helping and sharing their knowledge
وكلما كان الناس متعاونون ويساعدون بعضهم البعض
and providing mentoring,
ويقدمون التوجيهات
the better organizations do on every metric we can measure:
كلما كانت المنظمة أفضل
higher profits, customer satisfaction, employee retention --
أكثر ربحاً وإرضاءْ للعملاء، إستبقاءً للموظفين
even lower operating expenses.
أقل في المصروفات .
So givers spend a lot of time trying to help other people
المِعطاؤن يقضون الكثير مِن الوقت لمساعدة الآخرين
and improve the team,
وتطوير الفريق ،
and then, unfortunately, they suffer along the way.
لكن وللأسف يُعانون دائماً.
I want to talk about what it takes
اُريد أن أتحدث عن ما يتطلبه الأمر
to build cultures where givers actually get to succeed.
لنبني ثقافة يكون فيها المعطاؤن ناجحون.
So I wondered, then, if givers are the worst performers,
لذا تساءلت ، إن كان المعطاؤن هم الأسوأ في وظائفهم ،
who are the best performers?
مَن إذاً الأفضل ؟
Let me start with the good news: it's not the takers.
فالنبدأ بالأخبار الجيده : إنهم ليسوا هؤلاء الآخذين.
Takers tend to rise quickly but also fall quickly in most jobs.
الأشخاص الأنانيون يميلون إلى الصعود بسرعة لكنهم يسقطون بسرعة أيضاً.
And they fall at the hands of matchers.
يسقطون في يد هؤلاء الذين يعاملون بالمثل.
If you're a matcher, you believe in "An eye for an eye" -- a just world.
إن كنت ممن يُعامِل الناس بالمثل "العين بالعين "
And so when you meet a taker,
اذا قابلت شخص مُستغِل،
you feel like it's your mission in life
تشعر وكأن مهمتك بالحياة
to just punish the hell out of that person.
أن تعاقب هذا الشخص .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that way justice gets served.
وتخدم العدالة بهذه الطريقة .
Well, most people are matchers.
حسناً، أغلب الناس يعاملون بالمثل .
And that means if you're a taker,
وهذا يعني إن كنت شخص مُستغِل ،
it tends to catch up with you eventually;
سيلاحقك إستغلالك في النهاية ؛
what goes around will come around.
فكما تدين تُدان
And so the logical conclusion is:
لذا فالإستنتاج المنطقي هو :
it must be the matchers who are the best performers.
أن يكون الذين يعاملون بالمثل هم الافضل .
But they're not.
لكنهم ليسوا الأفضل .
In every job, in every organization I've ever studied,
في كل منظمة قمت بدراستها ،
the best results belong to the givers again.
أفضل النتائج هي من نصيب المِعطاؤن.
Take a look at some data I gathered from hundreds of salespeople,
فالننظر علي بعض البيانات المُجمعة من مِئات الناس
tracking their revenue.
تتبع عائداتهم .
What you can see is that the givers go to both extremes.
ما رأيك في حصول الِمعطاؤن علي أفضل وأسوأ النتائج
They make up the majority of people who bring in the lowest revenue,
هم يمثلون أغلبية العائدات القليلة،
but also the highest revenue.
والعائدات الكبيرة أيضاً.
The same patterns were true for engineers' productivity
كذلك الحال بالنسبة للمهندسين
and medical students' grades.
ودرجات طلبة الطب .
Givers are overrepresented at the bottom and at the top
يُمثل المِعطاؤن أغلبية في قمة وقاع
of every success metric that I can track.
كل مقياس للنجاح .
Which raises the question:
والذي يدعونا لنسأل:
How do we create a world where more of these givers get to excel?
كيف نجعل هؤلاء المعطاؤن مُتقدمون دائماً؟
I want to talk about how to do that, not just in businesses,
أُريد أن أتحدث عن كيفية عمل ذلك ، ليس فقط في العمل ،
but also in nonprofits, schools --
لكن في الأعمال المجانية والمدارس
even governments.
وحتى الحكومات .
Are you ready?
هل أنتم مستعدون ؟
(Cheers)
(هِتاف)
I was going to do it anyway, but I appreciate the enthusiasm.
سأفعل ذلك علي أي حال ،لكني أُقدِر الحماس .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The first thing that's really critical
الأمر شديد الأهمية
is to recognize that givers are your most valuable people,
أن تعرف بأن المِعطاؤن هم أكثر الناس قيمة،
but if they're not careful, they burn out.
لكنهم إن لم يكونوا حذرين،تُستنفَذ طاقتهم.
So you have to protect the givers in your midst.
لذا عليك أن تحفظ المِعطاؤن في المنتصف .
And I learned a great lesson about this from Fortune's best networker.
وقد تعلمت درس هام مِن أفضل العاملين علي الإنترنت
It's the guy, not the cat.
الرجل ليس القطة .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
His name is Adam Rifkin.
إسمه آدم ريفكين.
He's a very successful serial entrepreneur
هو رائد أعمال ناجح جداً
who spends a huge amount of his time helping other people.
يقضي الكثير من وقته في مساعدة الآخرين.
And his secret weapon is the five-minute favor.
وطريقته في ذلك هي ،معروف لمدة 5 دقائق ،
Adam said, "You don't have to be Mother Teresa or Gandhi
يقول آدم" لست مضطر أن تكون القديسة تريزا أو غاندي
to be a giver.
لتكون مِعطاء.
You just have to find small ways to add large value
فقط عليك أن تجد طرق بسيطة لتُضيف قيمة كبيرة
to other people's lives."
لحياة الناس ".
That could be as simple as making an introduction
هذا على بساطته ،قد يكون مقدمة
between two people who could benefit from knowing each other.
للتعارف بين شخصين ليستفيد كلُُ من معرِفة الآخر.
It could be sharing your knowledge or giving a little bit of feedback.
مِن الممكن أن تشارك معرفتك وتُعطي رأيك .
Or It might be even something as basic as saying,
أو حتى شئ بسيط كقولك ،
"You know,
"تعرف ،
I'm going to try and figure out
سأقوم بمحاولة
if I can recognize somebody whose work has gone unnoticed."
للتعرف علي شخص ما أُهمِل جهده".
And those five-minute favors are really critical
خمس دقائق المعروف هذه هامة جداً
to helping givers set boundaries and protect themselves.
لمساعدة المِعطاؤن أن يضعوا حواجز لحماية أنفسهم
The second thing that matters
الشئ الثاني المُهم
if you want to build a culture where givers succeed,
إن أردت أن تؤسس لثقافة يكون فيها المِعطاؤن ناجحون ،
is you actually need a culture where help-seeking is the norm;
فأنت بحاجة لثقافة تكون مساعدة الناس فيها هي الأساس
where people ask a lot.
حيث يسأل الناس كثيراً
This may hit a little too close to home for some of you.
هذا قد يبدوا قريباً جداً لبعضكم
[So in all your relationships, you always have to be the giver?]
اذاً هل عليك أن تكون دائماً مِعطاء ؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What you see with successful givers
ما نراه في الاشخاص المعطاءة الناجحة
is they recognize that it's OK to be a receiver, too.
أنهم لا مانع لديهم من أن يتلقوا مساعدة أيضاً
If you run an organization, we can actually make this easier.
إن كنت تدير مؤسسة يمكنك أن تجعل هذا أسهل .
We can make it easier for people to ask for help.
يمكن أن نجعل من السهل أن يطلب الناس المساعدة
A couple colleagues and I studied hospitals.
أنا وزميلان لي درسنا السلوك بالمستشفيات.
We found that on certain floors, nurses did a lot of help-seeking,
وجدنا بأنه في بعض الأحيان تقدم الممرضات مساعدة هائلة ،
and on other floors, they did very little of it.
وأحياناً يكونوا أقل مساعدة
The factor that stood out on the floors where help-seeking was common,
العامل المؤثر حيث كانوا يساعدون بعضهم،
where it was the norm,
حيث كانت المساعدة سلوك ،
was there was just one nurse whose sole job it was
كان وجود ممرضة واحدة والتي
to help other nurses on the unit.
تساعد الأخرين .
When that role was available,
عندما كان هذا الدور متوفر ،
nurses said, "It's not embarrassing, it's not vulnerable to ask for help --
قالت الممرضات،" أنه ليس محرِجاً أن نطلب المساعدة-
it's actually encouraged."
إنه أمر مُشجِع".
Help-seeking isn't important just for protecting the success
السعي للمساعدة ليست هامة فقط للحفاظ على النجاح
and the well-being of givers.
وسلامة المعطائين.
It's also critical to getting more people to act like givers,
بل للحصول علي المزيد من المِعطائين،
because the data say
لأن البيانات تقول بأن
that somewhere between 75 and 90 percent of all giving in organizations
ما بين 75% الى 90% من المساعدة بأي منظمة
starts with a request.
تبدأ بمجرد طلب .
But a lot of people don't ask.
لكن الكثير من الناس لا يطلبون
They don't want to look incompetent,
لا يريدون أن يبدوا أقل كفاءة،
they don't know where to turn, they don't want to burden others.
لا يعرفون الى من يلجأون ، ولا يريدون أن يكونوا عِبء
Yet if nobody ever asks for help,
فإذا لم يطلب أحد المساعدة،
you have a lot of frustrated givers in your organization
سيكون لديك الكثير من المِعطائين المُحبَطين في منظمتك
who would love to step up and contribute,
الذين يحبون أن يُساهموا،
if they only knew who could benefit and how.
إن علِموا فقط كيفَ ولمَن.
But I think the most important thing,
لكني أعتقد أن الشئ الأكثر أهمية هو ،
if you want to build a culture of successful givers,
إن اردت التأسيس لثقافة عطاء ناجحة،
is to be thoughtful about who you let onto your team.
لابد أن تختار رئيس الفريق بعناية .
I figured, you want a culture of productive generosity,
أعتقد بأنك بحاجة الى ثقافة الإنتاج الغزير،
you should hire a bunch of givers.
يجب أن تمتلك الكثير مِن المِعطائين
But I was surprised to discover, actually, that that was not right --
لكنني كنت مندهشاً لأجد بأن هذا خاطئ-
that the negative impact of a taker on a culture
لأن تأثير الشخص المُستَغِل
is usually double to triple the positive impact of a giver.
هو ضعف أو ثلاث أضعاف تأثير الشخص المُعطي.
Think about it this way:
فكر على هذا النحو:
one bad apple can spoil a barrel,
تفاحة فاسدة يمكن أن تُفسِد برميل ،
but one good egg just does not make a dozen.
ولكن بيضة واحدة جيدة لا يمكنها أن تجعل الباقي كذلك
I don't know what that means --
أنا لا أعرف معنى هذا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I hope you do.
لكني آمل أن تعرفوا أنتم
No -- let even one taker into a team,
فقط ضع شخص إستغلالي واحد في فريق ،
and you will see that the givers will stop helping.
وسترى أنهم سيتوقفون عن العطاء .
They'll say, "I'm surrounded by a bunch of snakes and sharks.
سيقولون، "نحن محاطون بثاعبين وقروش.
Why should I contribute?"
لماذا أُشارك إذاً؟"
Whereas if you let one giver into a team,
فإذا تركت شخص معطي في فريق،
you don't get an explosion of generosity.
لن تحصل على كرم كبير.
More often, people are like,
عادة يقول الناس ،
"Great! That person can do all our work."
"عظيم! بإمكان هذا الشخص أن يقوم بكل العمل"
So, effective hiring and screening and team building
لذا فإن إختيار الاشخاص ومراقبتهم وبناء فريق
is not about bringing in the givers;
لا يتعلق بجلب اشخاص مِعطائين
it's about weeding out the takers.
بل بطرد المُستَغلين .
If you can do that well,
إن استطعت أن تفعل هذا،
you'll be left with givers and matchers.
سيتبقى المِعطاؤن والذين يعاملون بالمثل
The givers will be generous
المِعطاؤن سيتعاملون بكرم
because they don't have to worry about the consequences.
لأنهم ليسوا مضطرين أن يخشوا العقبات.
And the beauty of the matchers is that they follow the norm.
والمميز في من يعاملون بالمثل أنهم سيتبعون السلوك العام .
So how do you catch a taker before it's too late?
اذاً كيف تعرف الشخص الإستغلالي قبل فوات الأوان؟
We're actually pretty bad at figuring out who's a taker,
نحن سيؤون في معرفة الشخص الإستغلالي،
especially on first impressions.
خاصة عند أول إنطباع .
There's a personality trait that throws us off.
هناك سمات شخصية مُحيّرة
It's called agreeableness,
وهي ما نُسميها بالوِفاق ،
one the major dimensions of personality across cultures.
وهي واحدة من الأبعاد الرئيسية للشخصية .
Agreeable people are warm and friendly, they're nice, they're polite.
الوفاقي هو شخص ودود ،لطيف و مهذب .
You find a lot of them in Canada --
تجد الكثير منهم بكندا -
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Where there was actually a national contest
حيث يظهر الأمر هناك بشكل قومي
to come up with a new Canadian slogan and fill in the blank,
يصل إلى شعار جديد ليملأ فراغ،
"As Canadian as ..."
"....كما الكنديين"
I thought the winning entry was going to be,
أعتقد أن الأمر سيكون كالآتي،
"As Canadian as maple syrup," or, "... ice hockey."
"كشراب القيقب الكندي "او "الهوكي الكندي"
But no, Canadians voted for their new national slogan to be --
لكن لم يصوت الكنديون ليكون شعارهم -
I kid you not --
أنا لا أمزح -
"As Canadian as possible under the circumstances."
"بقدر الإمكان كما الكنديين"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now for those of you who are highly agreeable,
الآن ولهؤلاء منكم الوفاقيون،
or maybe slightly Canadian,
او ربما كنديون ،
you get this right away.
يمكنكم تفهم ذلك .
How could I ever say I'm any one thing
كيف يمكن أن أحتفظ بصفاتي
when I'm constantly adapting to try to please other people?
عندما أضطر دائماً لإرضاء الناس ؟
Disagreeable people do less of it.
الغير وفاقيون يبذلون مجهود أقل .
They're more critical, skeptical, challenging,
هم حاسمون ،مشككون،
and far more likely than their peers to go to law school.
والأكثر قدرة على الإلتحاق لدراسة القانون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's not a joke, that's actually an empirical fact.
هذه ليست مزحة ،إنها حقيقة تجريبية.
So I always assumed that agreeable people were givers
لذلك طالما إفترضت بأن الوفاقيون مِعطاؤن
and disagreeable people were takers.
والغير وفاقيون هم دائما إستغلاليون.
But then I gathered the data,
وقمت بجمع بيانات
and I was stunned to find no correlation between those traits,
وكنت مذهولاً لأجد بأنه ليست هناك علاقة بين هذه السمات ،
because it turns out that agreeableness-disagreeableness
إتضح بأن الوفاق وعدمه هو
is your outer veneer:
المظهر الخارجي :
How pleasant is it to interact with you?
كم هو ممتعاً أن أتفاعل معك؟
Whereas giving and taking are more of your inner motives:
بينما الأخذ والعطاء هو مُحرِك داخلي :
What are your values? What are your intentions toward others?
ما هي قيمك؟ ما هي نيتك تجاه الأخرين؟
If you really want to judge people accurately,
إن أردت أن تحكم علي الناس بصدق،
you have to get to the moment every consultant in the room is waiting for,
يجب ان تصل للنقطة التي ينتظرها الاستشاريون،
and draw a two-by-two.
وترسم جدولاً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The agreeable givers are easy to spot:
الاشخاص الوفاقيون سهل التعرف عليهم:
they say yes to everything.
يقولون نعم لأي شئ.
The disagreeable takers are also recognized quickly,
الغير وفاقيون تعرفهم بسهوله ايضاً،
although you might call them by a slightly different name.
ويمكن أن تُطلق عليهم لقب آخر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We forget about the other two combinations.
نحن نتجاهل النوعين الآخرين.
There are disagreeable givers in our organizations.
يوجد في منظمتنا اشخاص مُعطية وغير وِفاقية
There are people who are gruff and tough on the surface
هم يظهرون بشكل فظ وغليظ
but underneath have others' best interests at heart.
لكن في داخلهم إهتمام كبير بالآخرين.
Or as an engineer put it,
أو كما يراهم المهندسون
"Oh, disagreeable givers --
"مِعطاؤن غير وِفاقيون--
like somebody with a bad user interface but a great operating system."
كشخص له مظهر سئ لكنه ماهر جداً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If that helps you.
إن كان ذلك سياعدك لتتفهم.
Disagreeable givers are the most undervalued people in our organizations,
الأشخاص المِعطاؤن كثيري الإعتراض غير مُقَدَّرين في مؤسستنا
because they're the ones who give the critical feedback
لأنهم دائماً يوجهون النقد
that no one wants to hear but everyone needs to hear.
الذي لا أحد يريد أن يسمعه.
We need to do a much better job valuing these people
يجب أن نعطي هؤلاء حقهم
as opposed to writing them off early,
بدلاً مِن إهمالهم ونقول
and saying, "Eh, kind of prickly,
"أنه شخص كثير الغضب
must be a selfish taker."
لابد أن يكون إستغلالي"
The other combination we forget about is the deadly one --
النوع الآخر الذي تركناه هو
the agreeable taker, also known as the faker.
الإستغلاليون الوفاقيون أو المُزيَّفون
This is the person who's nice to your face,
هو شخص لطيف أمامك،
and then will stab you right in the back.
لكنه سيطعنك من الخلف .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And my favorite way to catch these people in the interview process
وطريقتي المُفضلة لمعرفة هؤلاء هي
is to ask the question,
أن أسأل هذا السؤال،
"Can you give me the names of four people
"هل يمكن أن تذكر أسامي ل 4 أشخاص
whose careers you have fundamentally improved?"
قمت بتحسين حياتهم المهنية ؟"
The takers will give you four names,
الشخص الإستغلالي سيعطيك 4 أسماء ،
and they will all be more influential than them,
وسيكونوا أكثر نفوذا منه،
because takers are great at kissing up and then kicking down.
لأنهم ماهرون في التملُق والخيانة.
Givers are more likely to name people who are below them in a hierarchy,
المِعطاؤن سيذكرون أسامي لأشخاص أقل منهم،
who don't have as much power,
و ليس لديهم سُلطة،
who can do them no good.
فلا يستطيعون أن يساعدوهم.
And let's face it, you all know you can learn a lot about character
يمكنكم أن تتعلموا الكثير عن الشخصيات
by watching how someone treats their restaurant server
بمتابعة تصرف شخص في مطعم
or their Uber driver.
او تعاملهم مع سائقي أوبر
So if we do all this well,
اذاً إن كنا نستطيع فعل ذلك
if we can weed takers out of organizations,
إن كان بإمكاننا أن نتخلص من الإستغلاليين،
if we can make it safe to ask for help,
إن إستطعنا جعل طلب المساعدة أمر سهل ،
if we can protect givers from burnout
إن إستطعنا حماية المِعطائين من الإستغلال
and make it OK for them to be ambitious in pursuing their own goals
ليصبحوا طموحين فيما يخص أهدافهم
as well as trying to help other people,
ومساعدة الآخرين أيضاً،
we can actually change the way that people define success.
يمكننا بالفعل أن نغير مفهوم الناس عن النجاح
Instead of saying it's all about winning a competition,
بدلاً من يكون الأمر تنافسي ،
people will realize success is really more about contribution.
سيصبح متعلقاً بمدى مساعدة الآخرين
I believe that the most meaningful way to succeed
أؤمن بأن أفضل طرق النجاح
is to help other people succeed.
هي أن تُساعد الآخرين لينجحوا
And if we can spread that belief,
وإن إستطعنا نشر هذا الإعتقاد ،
we can actually turn paranoia upside down.
يمكننا أن نغير هذه البارانويا .
There's a name for that.
هناك مُسمى لذلك .
It's called "pronoia."
إنه "برونيا"
Pronoia is the delusional belief
وهي الإعتقاد الخاطئ
that other people are plotting your well-being.
بأن الناس يخططون ليساعدوك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That they're going around behind your back
بأنهم سيساندوك
and saying exceptionally glowing things about you.
أن يقولو أشياء استثنائية و مُبهجة عنك.
The great thing about a culture of givers is that's not a delusion --
الشئ العظيم عن ثقافة العطاء هي أنها ليست وهم -
it's reality.
إنها حقيقة
I want to live in a world where givers succeed,
أريد أن أعيش في عالَم حيث ينجح المِعطاؤن،
and I hope you will help me create that world.
آمُل أن تساعدوني لصنع هذا العالم
Thank you.
شكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)